<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hazelcast jet on Ensar Basri Kahveci</title>
    <link>https://basri.dev/tags/hazelcast-jet/</link>
    <description>Recent content in hazelcast jet on Ensar Basri Kahveci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2020 Ensar Basri Kahveci. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://basri.dev/tags/hazelcast-jet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hazelcast Jet 0.6: Dynamic Scale out of Streaming Jobs
</title>
      <link>https://basri.dev/posts/2018-05-21-hazelcast-jet-06-dynamic-scale-out-for-streaming-jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basri.dev/posts/2018-05-21-hazelcast-jet-06-dynamic-scale-out-for-streaming-jobs/</guid>
      <description>I published this post at Hazelcast blog and put a copy here.
In Hazelcast Jet 0.5, we introduced fault tolerance for streaming computations. Hazelcast Jet periodically takes snapshots of the state of a running job and stores these snapshots in Hazelcast IMaps. In case of a failure, the job is restarted from the last successful snapshot. Hazelcast Jet 0.6 uses the same snapshotting mechanism to enable dynamic scaling of streaming jobs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing Guarantees in Hazelcast Jet</title>
      <link>https://basri.dev/posts/2018-03-01-processing-guarantees-in-hazelcast-jet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basri.dev/posts/2018-03-01-processing-guarantees-in-hazelcast-jet/</guid>
      <description>I published this post at Hazelcast blog and put a copy here.
Stream processing is a paradigm for on-the-fly processing of unbounded data feeds. We have been witnessing that stream processing engines (SPEs) get more attention every day in the era of fast data and become a fundamental component of data processing pipelines. They usually run in distributed settings to be able to cope with the flood of incoming data entries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hazelcast Jet 0.5: Fault Tolerant Stream Processing Made Easy
</title>
      <link>https://basri.dev/posts/2017-12-06-hazelcast-jet-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basri.dev/posts/2017-12-06-hazelcast-jet-05/</guid>
      <description>I published this post at Hazelcast blog and put a copy here.
Stream processing is an emerging computational paradigm for on-the-fly processing of live data feeds, targeting low latency and high throughput. Streaming applications are usually deployed on multiple servers to achieve these requirements. Since even a single failure may lead to incorrect results or long interruptions in result delivery, fault tolerance is of paramount importance in such long-running distributed applications.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>