<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks on Ensar Basri Kahveci</title>
    <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks on Ensar Basri Kahveci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://basrikahveci.com/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>java.util.concurrent for Distributed Coordination
</title>
      <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2019-java-util-concurrent-for-distributed-coordination/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2019-java-util-concurrent-for-distributed-coordination/</guid>
      <description>I gave this talk at the following conferences:
 Devoxx Ukraine, November 2019 Berlin Expert Days, September 2019 Devoxx Poland, June 2019 IMC Summit Europe - London, June 2019 Riga Dev Days, May 2019 GeeCON Krakow, May 2019 JEEConf Kyiv, April 2019  Abstract The evolution of distributed coordination tools shows that high-level APIs ease implementation of coordination tasks, such as leader election, locking, synchronized actions. For instance, the Chubby paper highlights familiarity of lock-based interfaces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replication Distilled: Hazelcast Deep Dive
</title>
      <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2018-replication-distilled-hazelcast-deep-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2018-replication-distilled-hazelcast-deep-dive/</guid>
      <description>I gave this talk at the following conferences:
 Topconf Tallinn, November 2018 IMC Summit NA - San Francisco, October 2018 Berlin Expert Days, September 2018 JDK.IO, July 2018  Abstract Distributed data stores cope with the challenges of managing replicated data. Building a distributed data store is hard, and clarifying its high level properties is even harder. Hazelcast makes use of several replication techniques to offer choices for the trade-offs between consistency, availability, and latency properties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Systems Theory for Mere Mortals
</title>
      <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-distributed-systems-theory-for-mere-mortals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-distributed-systems-theory-for-mere-mortals/</guid>
      <description>I gave this talk at the following conferences and meetups:
 Software Craftsmanship Turkey Meetup Istanbul, December 2017 Topconf Dusseldorf, October 2017 GeeCON Krakow, May 2017 Javaday Istanbul, May 2017 Goto Chicago (Sponsored), May 2017  Abstract This is a light talk about the fundamental topics of distributed systems theory. It introduces a few theoretical system models, and briefly discusses how they reflect to real world problems. It talks about the concept of time, how we perceive and use it to order things in distributed systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replication in the Wild
</title>
      <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-replication-in-the-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-replication-in-the-wild/</guid>
      <description>I gave this talk at the following meetups:
 Warsaw Cloud Native Meetup, May 2017 Ankara Cloud Meetup - London, March 2017  Abstract A survey-like presentation about various replication techniques widely-used in distributed databases and NoSQL products.
Slides You can view and download the slides here.
Recording in English You can watch the English version of this talk here.
Recording in Turkish   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Client-centric Consistency Models
</title>
      <link>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-client-centric-consistency-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basrikahveci.com/talks/2017-client-centric-consistency-models/</guid>
      <description>I gave this talk at an internal engineering event of Hazelcast.
Abstract A brief presentation about client-centric consistency models and how they can be modeled on Hazelcast.
Slides You can view and download the slides here.
Recording There is no recording available for this talk.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>